<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title lang="eng">Vairocana and the Eight Bodhisattvas (Stein Painting 50)</title>
        <author lang="eng">Heller, Amy</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>IDP</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>2014</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>
          <ref>Tibetan Studies: Proceedings of the 6th International Seminar of the International Association for Tibetan Studies, Fagernes 1992, Oslo (The Institute for Comparative Research in Human Culture)</ref>
        </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>Translation</projectDesc>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <head>
      <p>This catalogue brings together the work of Amy Heller on Stein Painting 50, identified as an image of the buddha Vairocana surrounded by the eight bodhisattvas, correcting a previous identification of the central figure as Amitābha. The main text was first published in Kværne, P. (ed.), <title lang="eng">Tibetan Studies: Proceedings of the 6th International Seminar of the International Association for Tibetan Studies, Fagernes 1992, Oslo (The Institute for Comparative Research in Human Culture)</title>, 1994, vol.1, pp.335-49 and Appendix to Volume 1, pp.12-19.
    </p>
    </head>
    <body>
      <msDescription n="1" type="AH">
        <msIdentifier>
          <settlement>London</settlement>
          <institution>The British Library</institution>
          <collection>Stein</collection>
          <idno type="current">1919,0101,0.50</idno>
        </msIdentifier>
        <msContents>
          <msItem n="all">
            <title lang="eng">Vairocana with the eight bodhisattvas.</title>
            <note>
              <p>Among the paintings recovered from Dunhuang, the British Museum possesses an example previously identified as Amitābha accompanied by the eight Bodhisattvas. This painting has several inscribed cartouches written in Tibetan, and is believed to have been painted during the Tibetan occupation of Dunhuang. In many respects, the iconography and composition of this representation are virtually identical with the lDan ma brag Vairocana. Beneath a canopy, the gold-color Buddha is crowned, hair in braids, dressed in dhoti and adorned with jewelery, his hands in <term lang="san">dhyāna mūdra</term>; the eight Bodhisattva surround the Buddha in two rows of four. The costumes of the Dunhuang scroll are inspired by Indian garments. The lotus pedestal and lion throne beneath the central figure are quite similar to the lDan ma brag carving. Two distinguishing factors for Amitābha, the peacock vehicle and the color red, are notably absent from the Dunhuang painting. Although no certain identifications may be made of the eight Bodhisattva surrounding the Buddha of the rock carving, in the light of the iconographic information presented here, the question may be raised whether the two compositions indeed represent a particular treatise then popular, associating the eight Bodhisattva with Vairocana. In addition to the Tibetan representations, Chinese, Central Asian, and Indian examples of this iconography have been identified, all firmly dated (by virtue of excavation) to the eleventh century or earlier. 
		    </p>
            </note>
            <listBibl/>
            <!-- Bibliography to be adjusted when we have decided on format for new IDP database/website and XSLT (entry_cat.xsl) has been edited (SvS Sept 2014) -->
            <note>
              <p>Amy Heller. "P.T. 7a, P.T. 108, P.T. 240 and Beijing bsTan 'gyur  3489: Ancient Tibetan rituals dedicated to Vairocana", in R. Vitali, ed. The Pandita and the Siddha, Tibetan Studies in honor of E. Gene Smith. Dharamsala: Library of Tibetan Works and Archives. 2007: 85-91.</p>
              <p>Amy Heller. Early Ninth Century Images of Vairochana from Eastern Tibet" Orientations 25/6 (1994): 74-79.</p>
              <p>Amy Heller. "Ninth century Buddhist images carved at lDan-ma-brag to commemorate Tibeto-Chinese negotiations" in P. Kvaerne  ed. Tibetan Studies, Proceedings of the 6th Seminar of the International Association for Tibetan Studies, Fagernes 1992. Oslo: The Institute for Comparative Research in Human Culture, 1994: 335-349; (separatum) Appendix pp. 12- 19.</p>
              <p>Amy Heller. "Eighth and ninth century temples and rock carvings of Eastern Tibet" in J.C. Singer and P. Denwood, eds. Tibetan Art, Towards a Definition of Style, London: Laurence King, 1997: 86-103; footnotes pp. 296-297.</p>
              <p>Amy Heller. "Buddhist images and rock inscriptions from Eastern Tibet, Part IV" in H. Krasser, M. T. Much, E. Steinkellner and H. Tauscher, eds. Tibetan Studies, Proceedings of the 7th Seminar of the International Association for Tibetan Studies, Graz 1995. Wien: Verlag der Österreichischen Akademie der Wissenschaften, 1997: 385-403.</p>
            </note>
          </msItem>
        </msContents>
      </msDescription>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
