<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Sogdian Ancient Letters: 1, 2, 3, and 5</title>
        <author id="TB">Nicholas Sims-Williams</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>International Dunhuang Project</publisher>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <date>2013</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>2nd electronic edition, (1st electronic edition, Silk Road
                    Seattle).</edition>
        <date>2013</date>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Converted to XML encoding</resp>
          <name>
            <persName>Sam van Schaik</persName>
            <orgName>International Dunhuang Project</orgName>
          </name>
        </respStmt>
      </editionStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>http://depts.washington.edu/silkroad/texts/sogdlet.html</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <projectDesc>XML (TEI) mark up of HTML version
                (http://depts.washington.edu/silkroad/texts/sogdlet.html).</projectDesc>
      <editorialDecl>Imported to 4D on 18/09/2013 by Sam van Schaik.</editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <head>
      <p>The current electronic text is based on the online version 
                hosted on the Silk Road Seattle website, a project of the Simpson Center for the
                Humanities at the University of Washington and the Silkroad Foundation (<link url="http://depts.washington.edu/silkroad/texts/sogdlet.html">click
                    here</link>).</p>
      <p>Dan Waugh provided IDP with the html file
                which is the basis of the current XML version. The original preface is
                reproduced immediately below.</p>
      <p>ORIGINAL INTRODUCTION by Prof. Daniel C. Waugh, University of Washington (2004)</p>
      <p>The Sogdians, a people of Iranian origin, were important in the commerce of the Silk
                Road between the fourth and ninth centuries CE. From their home in the region near
                today's Samarkand in Central Asia (their core territory straddled what is now
                southern Uzbekistan and Western Tajikistan), Sogdian merchants traveled across
                Eurasia. Chinese chronicles noted their commercial acumen; members of the Sogdian
                colonies established in China came to function as administrators. The Sogdian
                language was used widely for communication along the trade routes, and Sogdians were
                among the translators of Buddhist scriptures in China. The Sogdian presence in what
                is now northern Pakistan is attested by inscriptions carved on rocks in the remote
                mountain valleys through which the trade routes passed. Archaeologists have
                uncovered in the Sogdian city states of Central Asia impressive architecture and
                painting which help document a flourishing cosmopolitan urban culture of a people
                who themselves never created a great empire.</p>
      <p>Among the most important documents of Sogdian history are five nearly complete
                letters, discovered in 1907 by the famous British archaeologist Aurel Stein in a
                Chinese watch tower just west of the Jade Gate, a fortified outpost guarding the
                western approaches to the administrative and cultural center of Dunhuang (at the
                western end of today's Gansu Province). Stein's discovery was some 90 km. west of
                Dunhuang and 550 km. east of Lou-lan, another important outpost on the southern
                branch of the silk route, which skirted the Taklamakan Desert. It seems likely that
                the letters were confiscated by a Chinese garrison at a time when Chinese control
                this far west was being threatened. While there has been considerable controversy
                over the dating of the letters, the most persuasive arguments (supported by Prof.
                Sims-Williams and his colleagues) point to 313 (-314) C.E. Two of the letters were
                sent by a lady in distress who had been abandoned in Dunhuang (nos. 1 and 3); the
                other two letters reproduced here (nos. 2 and 5) concern commercial activity of the
                writers. While a whole archive of Sogdian documents from several centuries later has
                been discovered in Central Asia, the Sogdian ancient letters are the earliest
                substantial examples of Sogdian writing and thus provide extremely important
                information about the early history of the Sogdian diaspora along the eastern end of
                the silk route.</p>
      <p>The author of letter 2 likely was resident in Jincheng (today, Lanzhou), a town in
                Gansu at the gateway to the Hexi Corridor, the passage between the southern
                mountains and northern deserts which leads to Dunhuang. He was writing to the "home
                office" in Samarkand. The first part of the letter concerns the Sogdian diaspora in
                China and contains the information about the destruction by the Huns of two
                important Chinese cities, Yeh and the then capital, Luoyang (the latter occurred in
                311 CE). The second part of the letter concerns the distribution of funds that the
                writer had apparently left on deposit at home.</p>
      <p>The author of letter 5 was writing from Guzang, the modern Wu-wei, located northwest
                of Luoyang in the Hexi Corridor. The addressee of the letter may have been resident
                in Khotan, an important town along the southern silk route just before it crosses
                the Pamir Mountains to reach the oases of Transoxania, the region between the Amu
                Darya and Syr Darya rivers. This letter also refers to the chaos and difficult
                conditions in China; the author's position had apparently been made the more
                difficult when his commercial partner, Ghawtus, abandoned him. Thus the author was
                forced to return from Dunhuang to Guzang.</p>
      <p>The letters include the names of several products--silver, linen and a kind of
                unprocessed cloth, musk (whose source was Tibet), pepper, and "white" (probably
                white lead powder, a valuable commodity used in cosmetics and drugs). Unfortunately
                the meaning of some terms for other products is not known. It appears from the
                quantities mentioned that the trade was relatively small-scale and, as we might
                expect, focussed on goods with high value for the weight.</p>
      <p>Bibliography (provided by Prof. Sims-Williams):</p>
      <p>Etienne de la Vaissière, Histoire des marchands sogdiens (Bibliothèque de l'Institut
                des Hautes Études Chinoises 32) (Paris: 2002).</p>
      <p>For further details concerning letter 2, including the Sogdian text and linguistic
                commentary, see N. Sims-Williams, "The Sogdian Ancient Letter II," in M. G. Schmidt
                and W. Bisang (ed.),<title lang="ger">Philologica et Linguistica. Historia, Pluralitas, Universitas.
                Festschrift für Helmut Humbach zum 80. Geburtstag am 4. Dezember 2001</title>(Trier:
                Wissenschaftlicher Verlag, 2001): 267-280. Colour photographs of the manuscript are
                included in A. L. Juliano and J. A. Lerner,<title lang="eng">Monks and Merchants: Silk Road Treasures
                from Northwest China</title>(New York: Harry N. Abrams with The Asia Society, 2001): 47-48.
                On the date of the letter and the historical data contained in it see F. Grenet and
                N. Sims-Williams, "The historical context of the Sogdian Ancient Letters," in<title lang="eng">Transition periods in Iranian history, Actes du Symposium de Fribourg-en-Brisgau
                (22-24 Mai 1985)</title>(Leuven: E. Peeters, 1987): 101-122.</p>
      <p>For further details concerning letter 5, including the Sogdian text, photographs of
                the manuscript and historical and linguistic commentary, see F. Grenet, N.
                Sims-Williams and E. de la Vaissière, "The Sogdian Ancient Letter V," in<title lang="eng">Bulletin of
                the Asia Institute</title>, 12 (1998 [2001]) (=Alexander¹s Legacy in the East: Studies in
                Honor of Paul Bernard): 91-104.</p>
      <p>On Letters 1 and 3 see<title lang="eng">The Silk Road: Trade, travel, war and faith</title>(ed. S. Whitfield
                with U. Sims-Williams), London, 2004, pp. 248-9, which also includes colour
                photographs of both letters. N. Sims-Williams’ edition of Letter 1 with detailed
                commentary will appear in an article entitled “Towards a new edition of the Sogdian
                Ancient Letters” in the proceedings of the conference Les sogdiens en chine,
                Beijing, April 2004 (to be edited by Eric Trombert and E. de la Vaissière and
                published by the Ecole Française d’Extrême-Orient). A similar edition of Letter 3 is
                in preparation.</p>
      <p>Translations © 2004 Nicholas Sims-Williams. Permission to reproduce them must be
                obtained from Prof. Sims-Williams (ns5@soas.ac.uk)</p>
      <p>Introduction © 2004 Daniel C. Waugh (dwaugh@u.washington.edu)</p>
    </head>
    <body>
      <msDescription n="1">
        <msIdentifier>
          <settlement>London</settlement>
          <repository>The British Library</repository>
          <collection>Stein</collection>
          <idno type="current">Or.8212/92(1)</idno>
        </msIdentifier>
        <msContents>
          <msItem n="Verso">
            <q lang="sog">From her daughter, the free-woman Miwnay, to her d[ear] mother
                            [Chatis].</q>
          </msItem>
          <msItem n="Recto">
            <q lang="sog">
              <p>[From her dau]ghter, the free-woman Mi[wnay], to her dear
                                [mother] Chatis, blessing and homage. It would be a good day for him
                                who might [see] you healthy and at ease; and [for me] that day would
                                be the best when we ourselves might see you in good health. I am
                                very anxious to see you, but have no luck. I petitioned the
                                councillor Sagharak, but the councillor says: Here there is no other
                                relative closer to Nanai-dhat than Artivan. And I petitioned
                                Artivan, but he says: Farnkhund ..., and I refuse to hurry, I refuse
                                to ... And Farnkhund says: If your husband’s relative does not
                                consent that you should go back to your mother, how should I take
                                you? Wait until ... comes; perhaps Nanai-dhat will come. I live
                                wretchedly, without clothing, without money; I ask for a loan, but
                                no-one consents to give me one, so I depend on charity from the
                                priest. He said to me: If you go, I will give you a camel, and a man
                                should go with you, and on the way I will look after you well. May
                                he do so for me until you send me a letter!</p>
            </q>
          </msItem>
        </msContents>
      </msDescription>
      <msDescription n="2">
        <msIdentifier>
          <settlement>London</settlement>
          <repository>The British Library</repository>
          <collection>Stein</collection>
          <idno type="current">Or.8212/95</idno>
        </msIdentifier>
        <msContents>
          <msItem n="Envelope">
            <q lang="eng">
              <p>. . . should send and bring [this] letter to Samarkand. And [the
                                noble lord Varzakk . . . should receive(?)] it all(?) [complete(?)].
                                Sent [by his] servant Nanai-vandak.</p>
            </q>
          </msItem>
          <msItem n="Verso">
            <q lang="eng">
              <p>To the noble lord Varzakk (son of) Nanai-thvar (of the
                                family) Kanakk. Sent [by] his servant Nanai-vandak.</p>
            </q>
          </msItem>
          <msItem n="Recto">
            <q lang="eng">
              <p>To the noble lord Varzakk (son of) Nanai-thvar (of the
                                family) Kanakk, 1,000 (and) 10,000 (times) blessing (and) homage on
                                bended knee, as is offered to the gods, sent by his servant
                                Nanai-vandak. And, sirs, (it would be) a good day for him who might
                                see you happy (and) free from illness; and, sirs, (news of) your
                                (good) health having been heard (by me), I consider myself
                                immortal!</p>
              <p>And, sirs, Armat-sach in Jiuquan (is) safe (and) well and Arsach in
                                Guzang (is) safe (and) well. And, sirs, it is three years since a
                                Sogdian came from "inside" [i.e. from China]. I settled(?)
                                Ghotam-sach, and (he is) safe (and) well. He has gone to Kwr¹ynk,
                                and now no-one comes from there so that I might write to you about
                                the Sogdians who went "inside," how they fared (and) which countries
                                they reached. And, sirs, the last emperor, so they say, fled from
                                Luoyang because of the famine, and fire was set to his palace and to
                                the city, and the palace was burnt and the city [destroyed]. Luoyang
                                (is) no more, Ye (is) no more! Moreover, the . . . Huns(?), and they
                                . . . Changan, so that they hold(?) it(?) . . . as far as N'yn'ych
                                and as far as Ye, these (same) Huns [who] yesterday were the
                                emperor's (subjects)! And, sirs, we do not know wh[ether] the
                                remaining Chinese were able to expel the Huns [from] Changan, from
                                China, or (whether) they took the country beyond(?). And [. . . in .
                                . . there are] a hundred freemen from Samarkand . . . in [. . .]
                                Dry'n there are forty men. And, sirs, your [. . . it is] three years
                                since [. . . came] from "inside" . . . unmade (cloth)(?). And from
                                Dunhuang up to Jincheng in . . . to sell, linen cloth is going [=
                                selling well?], and whoever has unmade (cloth)(?) or<term lang="sog">raghzak</term>(which is) not (yet) brought (to
                                market)(?), not (yet) taken, [can](?) sell [all](?) of it . . . And,
                                sirs, as for us, whoever dwells (in the region) from Ji[ncheng](?)
                                up to Dunhuang, we (only) survive [lit. "have breath"] so long as
                                the . . . lives, and (we are) without family(?), both old and on the
                                point of death. If this were not (so), [I would] not be ready(?) to
                                write to you (about) how we are. And, sirs, if I were to write to
                                you everything (about) how China has fared, (it would be) beyond(?)
                                grief: there is no profit for you (to gain) therefrom. And, sirs, it
                                is eight years since I sent Saghrak and Farn-aghat "inside" and it
                                is three years since I received a reply from there. They were well .
                                . ., (but) now, since the last evil occurred, I do [not] receive a
                                reply from there (about) how they have fared. Moreover, four years
                                ago I sent another man named Artikhu-vandak. When the caravan
                                departed from Guzang, Wakhush[akk] the . . . was there, and when
                                they reached Luoyang, bo[th the . . .] and the Indians and the
                                Sogdians there had all died of starvation. [And I] sent Nasyan to
                                Dunhuang, and he went "outside" [i.e. out of China] and entered
                                (Dunhuang), (but) now he has gone without (obtaining) permission
                                from me, and he has (received) a great retribution and was struck
                                dead in the . . .</p>
              <p>Lord Varzakk, my greatest hope is in your lordship! Pesakk (son of)
                                Dhruwasp-vandak holds 5[...]4 staters from me and he put it on
                                deposit(?), not to be transferred, and you should hold [it . . .]
                                sealed from now (on), so that without (my) permission . . .
                                Dhruwasp-van[dak] . . .</p>
              <p>[Lord] Nanai-thvar, you should remind Varzakk that he should
                                withdraw(?) this deposit(?), and you should (both) count [it], and
                                if the latter is to hold it, then you should (both) add(?) the
                                interest to the capital and put it in a transfer document, and you
                                (Nanai-thvar) should give this too to Varzakk. And if you (both)
                                think (it) fit that the latter should not hold it, then you should
                                (both) take it and give it to someone else whom you do think fit, so
                                that this money may thereby become more. And, behold, (there is) a
                                certain orphan . . . dependent(?) on this income(?), and if he
                                should live and reach adulthood [lit. "years"], and he has no hope
                                of (anything) other than this money, then, Nanai-thvar, (when) it
                                should be heard that Takut has departed(?) to the gods -- the gods
                                and my father¹s soul (will) be a support(?) to you! -- and when
                                Takhsich-vandak is grown up [lit. "big"], then give him a wife and
                                do not send him away from yourself. Mortal(?) gratification(?) has
                                departed(?) from us(?) in the . . ., because (from) day (to) day we
                                expect murder(?) and robbery. And when (the two of) you need cash,
                                then you (Nanai-thvar) should take either 1,000 staters or 2,000
                                staters out of the money. And Wan-razmak sent to Dunhuang for me 32
                                (vesicles of) musk belonging to Takut so that he might deliver them
                                to you. When they are handed over you should make five shares, and
                                therefrom Takhsich-vandak should take three shares, and Pesakk
                                (should take) one share, and you (should take) one share..</p>
            </q>
          </msItem>
          <msItem n="Verso">
            <q lang="eng">
              <p>This letter was written [lit. "made"] when it was the year
                                thirteen of Lord Chirth-swan in the month Taghmich.</p>
            </q>
          </msItem>
        </msContents>
      </msDescription>
      <msDescription n="3">
        <msIdentifier>
          <settlement>London</settlement>
          <repository>The British Library</repository>
          <collection>Stein</collection>
          <idno type="current">Or.8212/98</idno>
        </msIdentifier>
        <msContents>
          <msItem n="Verso">
            <q lang="eng">
              <p>[Verso] From (his) daughter Shayn to the noble lord
                                Nanai-dhat.</p>
              <p>[On another part of the verso] From (his) servant [left
                                unfinished].</p>
            </q>
          </msItem>
          <msItem n="Recto">
            <q lang="eng">
              <p>To (my) noble lord (and) husband Nanai-dhat, blessing (and)
                                homage on bended knee, as is offered to the gods. And (it would be)
                                a good day for him who might see you healthy, happy (and) free from
                                illness, together with everyone; and, sir, when I hear (news of)
                                your (good) health, I consider myself immortal!</p>
              <p>Behold, I am living ..., badly, not well, wretchedly, and I consider
                                myself dead. Again and again I send you a letter, (but) I do not
                                receive a (single) letter from you, and I have become without hope
                                towards you. My misfortune is this, (that) I have been in Dunhuang
                                for three years thanks(?) to you, and there was a way out a first, a
                                second, even a fifth time, (but) he(!) refused to bring me out. I
                                requested the leaders that support (should be given) to Farnkhund
                                for me, so that he may take me to (my) husband and I would not be
                                stuck in Dunhuang, (for) Farnkhund says: I am not Nanai-dhat’s
                                servant, nor do I hold his capital. I also requested thus: If he
                                refuses to take me to (my) husband, then ... such support for me
                                that he may take me to (my) mother. The leaders say: Here in
                                Dunhuang there is no other relative closer than Artivan, (but)
                                Artivan [say]s: Farnkhund ... whatever ... to do for you. If(?) I(?)
                                (had) no guarantee, no protection, my father ... I have become ...
                                not ... How much more would I have ... by my father if ... a servant
                                of the Chinese! A free man ... who found ... and ... keeps (his)
                                clothing in good condition(?). And you write (your) bidding to me
                                about everything in ... so that I should ... you and I should know
                                how to think, and if I do not ... you, then you write to me so that
                                I should know how to serve the Chinese. In my paternal abode I did
                                not have such a restricted ... as with(?) you. I obeyed your command
                                (lit. took your command upon my head) and came to Dunhuang and I did
                                not observe (my) mother’s bidding nor (my) brothers’. Surely(?) the
                                gods were angry with me on the day when I did your bidding! I would
                                rather be a dog’s or a pig’s wife than yours! And for me ...</p>
              <p>Sent by (your) servant Miwnay. This letter was written in the third
                                month on the tenth day.</p>
            </q>
          </msItem>
          <msItem n="Added in the margin">
            <q lang="sog">
              <p>From (his) daughter Shayn to the noble lord Nanai-dhat,
                                blessing (and) homage. And (it would be) a good [day] for him [who]
                                might see [you] healthy, rested (and) happy. ... I have become ...
                                and I watch over a flock of domestic animals. Differently to you, I
                                had a ..., and ... went out. I am ... and I know that you do not
                                lack twenty staters(?) to send. It is necessary to consider the
                                whole (matter). Farnkhund has run away; the Chinese seek him but do
                                not find him. Because of Farnkhund’s debts we have become the
                                servants of the Chinese, I together with (my) mother.</p>
            </q>
          </msItem>
        </msContents>
      </msDescription>
      <msDescription n="5">
        <msIdentifier>
          <settlement>London</settlement>
          <repository>The British Library</repository>
          <collection>Stein</collection>
          <idno type="current">Or.8212/94(A)</idno>
          <idno type="current">Or.8212/94(B)</idno>
          <idno type="current">Or.8212/100</idno>
        </msIdentifier>
        <msContents>
          <msItem n="Verso">
            <q lang="sog">
              <p>To the noble lord, the chief merchant Aspandhat. -- [Sent]
                                by your servant [Fri-khwataw].</p>
            </q>
          </msItem>
          <msItem n="Recto">
            <q lang="sog">
              <p>To the noble lord Aspandhat, blessing (and) homage. And (it
                                would be) a [good] day [for him] who might see you healthy (and)
                                safe, happy, free from illness (and) content. Fr[om Fri-khwataw]
                                your servant. And [for me the] day (would be still) better if [I
                                might see] you [my]self [and] might pay homage to you from nearby,
                                [as] (homage is offered) to the gods.</p>
              <p>[From] inside (China) [I] have heard worse, not better, (news) day
                                (by) day, and whatever I might write concerning A[khurmaztakk](?),
                                how he himself went (away) and what he had . . . I have become
                                isolated, and, behold, I stay here in Guzang and I do not go hither
                                (and) thither, and there is no caravan(?) (departing) from here. In
                                Guzang (there are) 4 bundles of "white" for dispatch, and 2,500
                                (measures of)(?) pepper for dispatch, and a double<term lang="sog">prasthaka</term>of<term lang="sog">n(••y)t</term>, and 5<term lang="sog">prasthaka</term>s of<term lang="sog">rysk</term>, and half a stater of silver. When Ghawtus went
                                (away) from Guzang I went after him, and I came to Dunhuang, (but) I
                                was prevented(?) from straying(?) outside (China). (If) . . .
                                Ghawtus had seen [=found?] a level route, then I would have brought
                                out the "Blacks." Many Sogdians were ready to leave, (but) they
                                could not leave, for Ghawtus went by(?) the mountains. I(?) would
                                (have) remain(ed) at Dunhuang, but they [=the Sogdian inhabitants]
                                were destitute. I depend(?) on charity(?) from your 'pr'k, for I am
                                serving(?) . . . in Guzang, and [they . . .] me, and they make me .
                                . ., and they obtain my . . ., [and] they increase (it) with our . .
                                . And . . . I am very wretched, and . . . the . . .</p>
              <p>I heard thus: Kharstrang [owed(?)] you twenty staters of silver, and
                                he declared(?) thus: I (will) bring(?) (it). He gave me the silver,
                                and I weighed it, and (there were only) four and a half staters
                                altogether. I asked: If he [sent] twenty staters, why do you give me
                                four and a half staters? He said thus: Aspandhat found me on the way
                                and he gave (it) to me(?). {He said thus: (There are) seven and a
                                half staters of silver.} And for four staters I obtained four loads
                                of<term lang="sog">'st(k)[•](m)</term>. And the "Blacks" took the
                                silver, for they said thus: We(?) have no money. For (according to
                                them it is) better (that) I should be wretched than they! (If) you
                                should hear how Akhurmaztakk has done me harm, then you should pay
                                heed (to this) too.</p>
              <p>Sent by your servant Fri-khwataw. This letter was written from
                                Guzang in the third month on the thirtieth (day).</p>
            </q>
          </msItem>
        </msContents>
      </msDescription>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI.2>
